this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software this is Robert for
software engineering a radio I am at the
Racine Revolution conference 2012 in
Boston with grant Ingersoll
is the chief scientist of lucid
imagination a committer on the solar and
the scene projects and the founder of
the Apache mahout project grants also
the author of the book taming text grant
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks Robert glad to be here grant and
I will be talking about search and the
solar search engine grant let's start
out what is search
so generally speaking search is
[Music]
something you want to do when you're
looking for some piece of informations
typically you're you know the way I
think about searching the way most
people who are using tools like leucine
and solar etc are think about searches
how can they put in a query using
keywords and/or natural language and
then get back relevant content whether
that's documents or images or whatever
such that it helps them better answer
the questions that they're asking
solar is a search engine that
applications can use now why would an
application want to implement its own
search
it's actually that's a great question I
mean there's a I think a number of
reasons
you know first off what many people have
done in the past around searches they
just use sequel queries and they do you
know if you're familiar with sequel like
queries they'll do you know they'll do
like and then star and then the word
that they're searching for followed by
another star you know so that they're
essentially doing some wild card queries
what typically happens in those
situations is the the results of the
search are not very good they're not
very relevant for what a user is doing
so then they look for better ways to
help users find content because you know
like I think what we've seen in a lot of
applications these days is they're very
data-driven and as soon as you have a
lot of data in your application you need
some way of searching through that so
whether it's a website or your social
media feeds or all of the content on
your desktop or across your your
enterprise you need some way of looking
through that content and so a search
engine will help you do those things and
then what many people find is if they
just go out and you know try to do that
through a database or just plug in some
appliance they often find that the
results aren't as good as they had hoped
and so by bringing that capability
in-house through a tool like we've seen
or solar you can often get much higher
quality results and you can also have of
course much more control over how and
when you do searches and and all the
related things that go along with search
you've mentioned comparisons to
databases a couple of times is a search
server like a database or how is it
different yeah I think it's yeah I mean
there's there's a lot of overlap paint
on on the one hand I mean of course a
database is you know primarily geared
towards doing relational type things I
mean that's you know traditional
databases my sequel Oracle etc you're
doing a set logic etc right whereas with
a search engine you actually have a bit
of different data structures underneath
the hood that are more geared for a
fuzzy matching and they're they're
geared for bringing back say the top ten
results or the top twenty results or
however many results as opposed to where
it was like a database where it's really
geared about you know giving you back
all of the results I'm actually of
course you can page through them as
database but if in a search engine it's
much more about what's relevant what
what the engine scores and thinks is
important as opposed to just you know
doing the set logic and defining which
things are in the satin which are not
how would you compare the type of data
records or data model of a search engine
to a database
it's actually one of the think one of
the really powerful things that people
are using search engines more and more
for us is a search engine is pretty
flexible when it comes to that you often
hear the word schema lists
kicked around when it comes to search
engines I'm not particularly a big fan
of that name but the idea here is that
you know a given document need not
conform to some strict rules you know a
column or format that like a database
does right so I can have one document
can have three fields on them and
another document could have a hundred
fields on them where you know
essentially a field here is the
equivalent of a column in a database
right and so you often have very
flexible capabilities when it comes to
dealing with documents of course there's
you know trade-offs there too you can't
always do all the things that you do
with a database but you can do most of
them in most cases and so you know you
can have you can have integers
primitives floats etc often you can also
of course have text and mostly in all
search engines so pretty flexible when
it comes to how you want to model your
content in databases or relational
databases we're used to
dividing things up the tables and
normalizing them there's any concept
like that exists in a search engine I
that's an interesting question I think
you know I mean to some extent you most
people who go and build out search
engines they do some upfront work to get
their documents into a reasonably normal
form it doesn't mean that you know every
they you necessarily do things
like you know foreign keys and primary
keys and all of that stuff but it does
typically mean that you have some
structure that you're overlaying on
these documents in terms of the fields
so you know you know if you think about
like a web page right well it's got a
title it's got a body it perhaps has
some meta tags like keywords etc so
oftentimes you'll model your search
documents that way you know by defining
what are the pieces of this document
that you want to be able to search
against
so the solar search engine is a
value-added layer on top of the scene
you break it down into what it was seen
and what is what is solar add to the
picture
sure so leucine is a core set of Java
libraries that is designed to handle
many of the the core things that one
needs when building out a search engine
so being able to convert strings into an
indexed format and then being able to
query in aquaria so it defines a number
of different ways of querying it the
index it also defines number of
different ways for getting content into
the index but at its heart leucine is
just a set of libraries that one would
have to then go and integrate into your
broader application the nice thing about
that is of course leucine can run on
everything from a mobile device all the
way up to you know very very large
scales like Twitter etc so you can you
know you can kind of build it you can
take what you need out of the scene and
build around and on top of it to build
out your search engine what most people
end up doing when they build on top of
leucine is to build something that looks
like solar which is a you know
essentially a restful service that
allows you to talk to leucine over over
HTTP or over a rust like interface right
so then you can just you know no matter
what your client is whether it's PHP or
Java or Ruby or whatever you can just
talk to solar over HTTP and do your
query into your indexing etc Solar also
has a number of other things that aren't
in in core leucine so it adds things
like faceting which some people think of
is either parametric search or guided
navigation it also adds in support for
scaling scaling vertically and scaling
horizontally so you can add servers that
can handle more and more loads as well
as handle larger and larger indexes you
mentioned faceting and scaling I would
like to come back to those next I'd like
to ask you what are the major resources
available in the restful api that of so
in terms of like the kinds of things
that you can ask a solar yeah what can
you um I think there's something you can
create objects and then you can get
objects to wear that sure so yeah so
that's so Soler's rest like I would say
it's just a pure rest api but it's you
know fairly similar and people who are
used to programming rest won't have a
problem with solar but you know on the
on the indexing side you get you of
course can push documents into it
essentially you're adding or creating
documents in the index as well as you
can update documents in the end I can
delete them you can do that in a variety
of different ways you can push in XML a
solar to find like an XML format you can
use you can also use JSON you can also
push in even you know what we call rich
office rich documents things like PDFs
and and Microsoft Office you can push in
and out of CSV files as well so there's
a wide variety of ways of getting
content in and then you can delete in a
variety of ways too you can delete by an
ID you can delete by a query so you
could actually specify hey here's I want
you to delete all the documents that
match this particular query so that
that's pretty expressive there on the
indexing side and then on the the query
Sider the get side if you like quite a
number of features there in fact both
we've seen up from you seen them and up
in the solar we provide a number of
different query parsers that allow users
to express their queries in a variety of
different ways so you can you typically
have users will say you know I want to
find the word I Triple E in the title
field and I want to find search in the
body field and so you can express
queries like that and you can get quite
complex so you can do basic keywords you
can do phrases you can do what are
called fuzzy queries so like if you want
to find based on perhaps introducing
wildcards into your query
is and a number of different things at
that time you can also ask for things
like facets you can ask for spell
checking so you've often I'm sure seen
on Google where if you misspell
something Google will say did you mean
you can do that right out of the box
with solar as well you can ask for solar
to take all of the results that it finds
for a query and to highlight them so in
other words find within the document
where the actual match occurred such
that you could then display that back up
and out to up and out to your users and
you know there's a whole variety of
other things I'm just barely scratching
the surface on what I understand from
your last comment is you can do more of
a sequel like expression where you're
doing exact matches on some terms mix
that in with a search type of operation
or you're doing a text search on other
terms is that correct
you can I mean with with essentially
this fielded syntax you can you can do
exact matches within fields you can do
fuzzy matches within fields you can look
for phrases you can look for terms near
each other you can also do some basic
join capabilities so that you can join
two documents which is often what
happens in the database but I won't go
in so far as the claim it's a full join
capability like one gets with sequel so
I I don't know if the sequel comparison
is totally accurate but I guess at the
end of the day there are a number of
different ways that allow you to go in
and dig into your index and ask you know
these kinds of questions of it that
you're perhaps used to join in sequel as
well
you mentioned faceting a couple of puns
please tell us what is faceting so
fascinating is is essentially a way of
narrowing down your search results with
known known values so it's probably the
best way is just to give an example if
you've been on most made most major
e-commerce sites these days like Amazon
or I don't know target.com or Walmart
com or any of the other ones they will
have when you do a search you will then
see often see on the left hand side what
are called facets and those things will
help you narrow down your search results
so for instance if you type in the word
TVs on the left hand side you'll often
see you know it broken down by price by
manufacturer by rating etc and those are
essentially what we call facets some
other search engines call them guided
navigators or databases often call it
parametric search so those are a number
of synonyms for faceting but then the
nice thing about facets is when a user
clicks on them it's going to filter down
the results but they they're guaranteed
to know that they're they're guaranteed
to get back those results right so if it
says that if the facet says there's five
Sony TVs when they click that up will
come five Sony TVs as the results and so
it's a way for
users to narrow down searches especially
when they're not quite sure how to put
in their query and you know what what
query terms to put in to find what
they're looking for we're being fair to
say then fastening enabled the
application designer to implement a kind
of a browsing type experience with a
drill down exactly exactly and in fact
we have at my company we have a number
of customers who you know applicated
their application doesn't even have a
search box on it but their entire site
or application is driven by search and
they're doing exactly what you're
talking about there they're using
queries plus facets underneath the hood
and all the pane on what the user clicks
on will then change the navigation
within the site and so it's very useful
for making highly dynamic websites I
think that is a great answer to my
earlier question why wait application
architects want to implement their own
search yeah no that's true we see that
we see that a number of times of course
many of them also have search boxes too
so but you know it's been interesting
for me that you know I started out just
doing you know pure text-based search
and you see you know over time you see
so many people doing things that are go
well beyond just pure text search and
are things like driving their whole
website off of the search engine
yeah becomes a kind of ubiquitous part
of the experience rather than a separate
feature it really is and that's why I
think you know we've seen a solar are so
powerful for so many people as you know
everybody just kind of needs to have
search in their application these days
it's almost taken for granted whereas
you know five six years ago you know is
maybe a bit more challenging to convince
people that they needed search in their
application whereas now I don't ever
have to explain that to people change
tracks of it here you mentioned that the
index several times tell us what is an
index
you know one of the I think the easiest
ways is to just think about the index in
the back of the book and the back of a
book right you you have a list of words
and what pages they occur on and then
you know so as a reader I can go to back
there and Excel this word occurs on page
I'll go look up number and write on that
page and see the context underneath the
hood and Lucene that's essentially
what's going on we keep a digging area
of all the words that we've seen and
then we keep track of what documents
they've occurred in and then you can
optionally also keep track of where
within the document they occurred and so
then when a query happens what happens
is the query comes in you go look up in
that dictionary what that term is and
then you know what page you know
essentially what documents of the Quran
and then you can go off and score those
documents so it makes for a very
efficient retrieval of matching
documents and then being able to score
those and of course you know in most
modern search engines there's all kinds
of tricks you would do to compress that
dictionary to compress the storage of
the you know what documents it occurs in
etc and you know leucine is no different
there and so you can often see like if
you have say a gigabyte of raw content
that you want to index the index itself
you know is often significantly smaller
than the original raw content I've seen
it in some cases it's as low as 15
percent of the original the image
persisted
it can be we actually have options for
it to just be in memory or to store
through store on disk most people in
most situations store on disk and then
and then just load that up when they
start up their system or do their
indexing or whatever but you know I've
seen applications that are essentially
transient they only index what's coming
through and it's only available while
the process is running and they don't
save it is the the end image of the
index typically larger than what could
fit in the memory on the server
of course change over the years given
how much memory one can get into server
these days but you know in in many cases
it is in many cases it's not it really
is going to depend on the amount of
content that you have and and the kinds
of things that you're asking the search
engine to do you know I've seen plenty
of applications you know if you have 16
32 you know 48 96 gigs of ram you know
your your index you know maybe even you
know 10 20 30 million documents or more
can often fit all the way in RAM so you
know it really depends on what your
goals are for performance etc as to how
you would want to do that but most
people in most situations just use a
file system back indexing the machine
does a very good job of loading the
memory the things that it needs in order
to be fast when a client application
pushes a document into solar you walk us
through the steps to take place to get
that document indexed
sure so well assuming it's one of the
more simpler forms and not like an
office document like I mentioned earlier
so say it's JSON or CSV or XML you know
it's essentially that kind of document
it looks like it has a bunch of fields
which are the keys and then the value is
the actual text that you want to index
and you know so solar comes in those
some you know fairly lightweight
pre-processing and then essentially
hands it off to leucine we've seen them
goes and takes the individual field than
their content and then depending on how
you have it configured it will
essentially try to convert that content
into into the dictionary that we use for
inside the index right so typically that
process is called analysis and what
we're doing there is taking and
tokenizing the the terms in the string
and then using those tokens as the
entries into the dictionary and of
course as you've seen as you've seen
tokens then you can keep track of you
know whether you've seen it before or
not and then go in and add the necessary
document IDs into the into the index
list right so that's a pretty basic
description of it we obviously do a lot
of things to make that fast and make
that efficient and to be able to still
serve queries while we're doing those
things but in a nutshell that's you know
you ingest the document you tokenize and
analyze the document the tokens that you
get out you shove into this inverted
index format that I described earlier
okay so you're updating this index and
you're also serving queries and
databases a transactional database is a
very strict consistency model for how
updates in read operations are
interleaved what sort of consistency
model does solar and racine provide
so you can do you know I think actually
we would say now that we're fully acid
compliant you can do you know
essentially a prepare and a commit if
you want most people don't need that
kind of transactionality and so was what
you have in many situations is what we
would call an eventually consistent
model whereby you know documents go into
the index ah in one hand and then at
some period the searches refresh its
view of the index essentially you up you
have this snapshot in time of the index
for serving up queries and then in your
application you can decide how often you
want to refresh that snapshot having
said that in the the newest release
that's coming out in in leucine and
solar you can change all of that such
that you can pretty much after every
document you can open up a new version
of the index and do queries against it
so that you see every can see every
document as it comes in so that's what
we call near real time searching that's
that's changed pretty significantly in
probably the last year to be a lot
higher performing than it was in the
past
but yeah I wouldn't say you know one of
the things I think a search engine
typically trades off as it's not a fully
transactional system like a database and
that's often fine for the kinds of
applications that people most use a
search engine for sure
well in many applications the updates
are coming from within the system itself
or from the business and the reads are
all done by the customers so if
somebody's adding say a new camera into
their inventory they really don't care
if the customer sees that camera now or
in ten seconds
exactly and that's exactly the that's
exactly why it's often designed that way
like I said there it is now possible
that you can pretty much see every
document as it comes in and so even that
case is handled much better now but but
yeah you're exactly right I mean if your
indexing Twitter you don't know whether
you know some new tweet came in one
second ago or five seconds ago so you
know as far as I you know I I have to
ask the system again for the results in
order to see the updates another
question about index is if you index
based on the words in the document and
you have queries with two or three words
or a phrase how does the index find out
so in the in the index we actually you
can keep track of the positions where
words occur and so then essentially
becomes a simple math problem of
determining what the distance is between
two words based on their positions you
can also do much more complex position
type things of saying you know this
phrase near that phrase or you know this
these words within the first you know
five positions of the start of the
document so that you can you can get
some fairly complex types of queries
that way we see and understand any data
types besides text like maybe date or
integer it does have some support for
numeric switch of course you can map
dates in to numerix and then you know
but you can you can overlay semantics
those kinds of semantics onto it solar
does have a much deeper understanding of
of primitives right so it supports
things like instant floats and doubles
and as well as just you know strings and
then we kind of we kind of call strings
and tacks so a string would be just the
literal and you have to do an exact
match on it whereas text we would say
gets tokenized and split up and do its
into its component words but at the end
of the day all of this just ends up
being a pretty straightforward a string
match underneath the hood and leucine
whether it's a number or whatever so you
know leucine itself doesn't have to care
but you can you can tell it to care if
you wanted to if that makes sense I
think that sounds like one of the major
differences with the record oriented
databases is it's really optimized
around text whereas a record oriented
you're doing a lot more strict data
typing yeah so I would say you know
solar that's especially the case with
leucine like I said we do have more
support for numerix now solar I think
has always had this over lane
type on top of it and so if you want to
learn be strict about types you can but
if you don't care about it then then you
don't have to and and so I think it
gives you a lot of flexibility that way
you know it's been interesting what like
I said earlier watching all this evolve
because I think you know search engines
in general have been taking on more
database like qualities whereas I think
databases perhaps have struggled a bit
more with taking on search qualities and
so you know I think in in solar
especially you can do a lot more things
that you're used to doing in a database
like you know applying functions on top
of numerics you can take the sum and
multiply it by things all you know so if
you have a field that's a numeric type
you can you can add to it you can
subtract from it you can sum it with
other fields all of those kinds of
things so you know that gets to be
pretty powerful for people who are
building out kinds of data-driven
applications and like I said earlier too
we've even added some join capabilities
as well I think probably one of the big
things that's missing so far as a
general-purpose aggregations or grouping
but even that we have we do have some
capabilities there and I think in the
pretty near future you'll see a lot more
when it comes to those kinds of things
where you're you want to say give me the
sum of the the values of this field
across all the documents that match
query right which can be pretty powerful
if I'm not planning application askew
grant ah here tour does do I need a
database joining us search engine do I
need both what's the division of labor
between them do you have some general
guidelines how you make that
recommendation
I mean it's you know I try not to be too
biased when it comes to any things
obviously I've been working on a search
a long time and think search engines are
great for a lot of things but you know
as an application developer as a
programmer it's your job to make the
appropriate choice of tools given given
the situation you're in so you know for
databases the things that it's good at
transactions
you know relational math etc that's the
best place to do in a database right if
you've got if you need to do joins if
you need primary key and foreign key
consistency etc that's that's where
database is belong if you're dealing
with a mixture of structured and I'll
use the word on structured although I
don't particularly like it on structured
text then the search engine often
becomes much more powerful because you
have this ability to do the fuzzy
matching against the the text part of
the the content and then combine that
with you know your application layer
understanding of the structured part of
it right so you can get and build out
some pretty complex things that way I've
also seen a number of cases where you
know just simply put the databases don't
scale to the size that a search engine
can do especially because if you can
denormalize your data a little bit I
think that often frees you up to be a
lot higher performing in your system so
you know it really does they'll come
down to what's the appropriate choice
for the tool I've seen many applications
that successfully use both of them in
conjunction I've seen cases where search
engines have just flat-out replaced the
database altogether I can't say that
I've ever seen the database fully
replaced the search engine now so I you
know even in when many of the database
vendors have tried to add search into
their system and you know
to some level of success I guess but I
don't think it ever is matched you know
a pure search engine capability once
we've got the data all in there next and
the query start coming in how does the
engine decide what are the most relevant
the search result out of all the ones
that it might match yeah that's a good
that's a great question I mean and it's
actually a pretty hard problem because
you know what's relevant to you and
what's relevant to me may be very
different if at the end of the day you
know a good chunk it's going to depend
on the way you're asking the query right
so if you're telling it you know you can
tell Lusine in solar like for instance
that you know this term and that term
must occur together somewhere in the
document or you can say things like you
know this term or that term or this term
and not that term you can also do the
phrases etc so what Lucene does is okay
you know it takes that query in and like
I said earlier it goes and looks in the
dictionary finds the possible candidates
for scoring and then essentially we have
a scoring model underneath the hood that
based on probably 40 to 50 years of
academic research has been proven out to
be pretty effective for scoring goes in
and determines what that score is based
on the criteria of the query now one of
the nice things actually in that's
coming in the next version of the scene
is you can actually even just plug in
your own scoring model so if you have a
different way of thinking about what's
relevant you can plug that right in and
Lucene will just continue to chug away
and produce results but you know if for
those who are more academically inclined
what we're what we primarily use is
what's called the vector space model so
if you if you remember your your
calculus or your trigonometry etc from
college or high school which ever
covered it for you if you take you can
think of a document as being a vector in
an n-dimensional space so if you
essentially each word
it's own you know its own cell within
that vector and then you can do the same
thing for the query and so then if you
bring the tails of those two vectors
together you'll have an angle that's
formed between those two and then what
typically happens is the search engine
in a search engine is if you take the
cosine of that angle you get a number
between minus 1 and 1 and if you
remember again your your trigonometry
you'll know that the cosine of 0 is 1 so
and I think intuitively that makes sense
that these two these two vectors overlap
each other and so that you would say yes
those are intuitively that's a that's a
relevant document whereas if the angle
is really large the cosine is going to
be you know either down toward 0 or
minus 1 so hopefully you know I mean
given the audience I think that should
be a hopefully a useful explanation this
is um the most relevant articles include
the outcome of a doing a sort where
you're able to compare each pair of
articles and say which one is more
relevant or is there anything like what
they do with Google Pagerank where the
position of each item in search result
of the property of the entire set and
how they're each one's it's related to
all the other articles so I mean you can
you can overlay something like PageRank
on top of this vector space model but I
mean at its heart the vector space model
really is just at the end of day comes
down to things like how many terms did
it does the query have in common with
the original document and then what is
the what are the importance of those
terms
mn as well you can have all their
factors like you know what's the length
of the document how many words are in
that document because I think you would
agree all else being equal I would order
document that has the query terms in it
is more relevant than a longer document
that has the query term
just because I think you know we would
all prefer to read get the answer sooner
right well he has a long enough document
it would have every word in itself right
orally our a lot of them and it would at
least it often has the the query terms
and at multiple times right so that's
what we call the term frequency and so
one of the things that we've seen does
is use the term frequency to determine
how important a particular word is it
offsets that term frequency by how often
that term occurs in the whole collection
so that's called the document frequency
or the inverse document frequency so
you'll hear in search speak you'll hear
a lot of people say things like tf-idf
waiting or tf-idf scoring and so
essentially at the end of the day what
we've seen is doing is given some query
term lookup what it's TF values are
lookup what it's IDF values are and then
do some math on that to determine you
know how important that word is and then
given all of those given that across all
of the terms in the query and in the
document you can then come up with a
score I and so there's various ways
lining those weights your best search
result and then your the usual word that
occurs frequently in a small document
but not very much else in the document
Center which that's exactly that will be
the most important word so what will
happen is those documents should rise up
as a top now of course in the same
because it's open source and because we
strive to make a lot of this pluggable
you can of course change them you know
I'm Chris if you think you have a better
model as we essentially use will be able
to enter and then what I'm parcel and we
see oh you shall with a phenom so
leucine core what you get from Apache
the the main flagship is in Java Soler's
as well the large majority of it is in
in Java but we do have there are a
number of libraries out there for other
languages that make it easy to connect
to solar
Lucine itself has been ported to pick a
language it's been ported to Python it's
been ported to Ruby it's been ported to
Perl it's been ported to C and ported
the objective-c I think it's imported to
even a few other hub variants in there
that I can't keep track of and then
typically in those porting on dotnet as
well typically those porting what
they're trying to do is maintain file
format consistency but they may then go
and change some of the api's to better
fit with that language that languages
you know view of the world when it comes
to creating api's but via the core
flagship what you get from the Pachi
that's all java tell us a little bit
about the history of the solar and we've
seen open source projects
sure so uh let's see if I can remember
it's been so long you know we've seen
itself is 15 or 16 years old at this
point you know like I said it builds on
top of you know 40 to 50 years of
academic research and pretty much
implements the standard way of doing
search that most of you know whether
you're buying a proprietary engine or
using some open source project the way
that they do search underneath the hood
I was started by Doug cutting for for
lists or familiar Doug is also the one
of the co-creators of the Hadoop project
which is pretty popular right now as
well as you start at the nudge web
crawling project so Doug started a
leucine as kind of a side project back
in the late nineties in fact it was a
way for him to learn Java which you know
for anybody out there who is going off
and learning a language they know they
don't they don't usually start with a
search engine as their first
implementation but Doug sure enough did
that and a little bit after that he put
it up on SourceForge and then in 2001
donated it to the Apache Software
Foundation where it's lived ever slipped
and grown ever since in roughly 2004 got
an MA Yannick Sealy and a few other
people that seen that started an
internal project that was building out
searches of service on top of leucine
and that is essentially the precursor to
solar solar was donated to Apache in
2006 and then has you know essentially
grown right alongside
Lucene over the years that's for me I
started using the scene in about 2004
and then
became a committer on the project in
2006 and then have been using machine
solar kind of ever since you know I
would say I guess the last thing I would
add is I mean leucine and solar power
some of the largest websites and
applications in the world it in my
estimation is the most widely used
search library on the planet you know
all that you know where it's somebody
can actually embed this into their
applications I'm not comparing it with
you know Google or Yahoo or any of those
web-based search engines for people who
need search in their applications we've
seen a solar are the the de-facto
choices in their an active community
around this new project yeah I mean as
you can imagine whether it being as
popular it is there's a lot of people
who are contributing code there's I
don't even lost count of the number of
committers these days ie the people who
can actually change the code add a patch
it's somewhere north of 30 people I
think and then the broader community is
in the thousands if not tens of
thousands I've seen you know estimates
as an applicant number of applications
using the seen solar arranging from you
know five thousand plus up through you
know hundreds of thousands so you know
it's one of those things just you know
with many open-source projects you you
just never know who's even using it but
you know it's everyday applications like
Wikipedia is powered by Lucene Netflix
is powered by solar Apple has the uses
we've seen a solar in a number of places
Twitter is powered by leucine and on and
on and on and so it's really you know
quite a quite an interesting span of
applications that are powered by leucine
and solar it's quite impressive
I didn't tell us about the relationship
of lucid imagination we scratched that
question I'm going to read a question
talk about the company lucid imagination
yep so lucid imagination is a company
that was founded for the sole purpose of
supporting and extending the
capabilities of Lusine and solar so in
many ways things like what Red Hat does
for Linux and their projects or my
sequel does for the my sequel database
we we aim to do that for leasing and
solar in the community we employ a large
number of the the contributors to it so
we contribute a lot of code back and
then we provide a range of services and
products around the scene and solar so
on the knowledge side of the equation we
do things like training we do support we
do professional services / consulting on
the product side we have a couple of
different products that build on top of
solar bring into it
things like content acquisition security
web-based administration capabilities
etc so you know really designed kind of
to make it many of the things that
people do when they're building out
applications on top of solar just bring
all of those into the fold into a single
product so they don't have to go out and
build those things themselves but we
still of course give you all the
capabilities of solar we don't want to
hide those from you for people who would
like to learn more about your work grant
do you blog or otherwise social media
where people can follow you sure yeah
its although my blogging has been a
little bit down lately because I've been
on a project deadline but uh I primarily
blog on lucid imaginations blog which is
just dub-dub-dub loose imagination calm
slash blog on Twitter
my handle is GS ing ers orgy singers
harking back to the old UNIX a character
username days that's
with me over the years so yeah G
singer's is my my tweet handle Twitter
handle and then like I said loosen
imagination calm this is where you can
usually find on blog posts
I realize there's one question I'm
supposed to ask right at the beginning
so this is a note the editor to put this
in right after I introduced grant the
question is grant please tell the
listeners about your background
sure yeah I'm Ben I'm the currently the
chief scientist at lucid imagination as
well as the co-founder I've been a
programmer since graduating college in
1996 I've done a wide variety of things
over the years I actually started my
career doing Fortran if you can believe
it doing electromagnetic simulations on
highly parallel distributed computing
then basically after that kind that gig
I happened on to a company that was
doing search in natural language
processing called text wise and and
started working on a cross language
search application so what that meant is
that you could put in your queries in
English and you could find content in
Japanese or French or Spanish like and
you didn't have to actually know that
language which is pretty cool
and that's really where I kind of fell
in love with search and natural language
processing as a career and so I've more
or less been doing that ever since
although I did have a small stint at a
company doing configuration management
which also has of course in number of
uses across these things but primarily
in the early days like I said doing
Fortran doing C C++ and then these days
you know doing doing a lot of Java I've
also been lately doing a lot more around
things like machine learning I'm also
one of the the founders of the mahout
project which is a all about building
out scalable machine learning libraries
and so that's all written primarily in
Java but designed also to run on top of
tools like Hadoop so I guess that's more
or less my background try to keep my my
hands dirty writing code these days so I
you know to keep up on those skills
mineralize had one more technical
question that I can he'll miss I know we
could probably spend a whole show
talking about scaling but could you
briefly talk about the scaling
capabilities of solar if you're either
your index or your volume of searches
outgrows what can run on one node sure
yes I mean from almost day one Solar has
supported really high query volumes what
is traditionally called a replicated
environment or replication environment
or sometimes people call it master
worker or master slave the idea that you
have one index that you know fits on a
single machine and then you just need to
pick copies of it and you you put all
those copies behind the load balancer
and then you know as your requests come
in you just fan them out to the
appropriate the appropriate available
for do pretty straight for a long time
and solar in more recent years we've
also added the ability to do distributed
indexing and searching and that's the
case where you have an index that
essentially is too large to fit on a
single single machine and so what you do
is you split it up across multiple nodes
these are often called shards and then
you every time a query comes in you fan
out that query to all of the shards have
each of them do the scoring and then
collate the results back up and out to
the user and of course these days with
the types of applications that people
are building you you actually need the
combination of these you need you know
the high you need to handle the high
query volume as well as the large
indexes and so then what you can think
of is essentially a building on a system
that more or less looks like a matrix
where every row is a shard and then
every column is a copy of that shard and
so you essentially have this grid
pattern right that you can then overlay
with a load balancer that can go and
figure out who's available for searching
and you know what shards need to be
queried and and all those things and all
of that's built right in the solar
can do it just out-of-the-box pretty
straightforward to set up and run and
and you typically just can add hardware
as as you needed one of the things we're
very actively working on the community
is to make that even easier to make the
whole management of that easier as you
grow out so you know right now we've got
you know I loo sittin in the community
we've got customers and community
members who pretty easily handle
billions and billions of documents in
solar and we're you know really looking
to take that to the next level even
above and beyond that right so skills
out pretty effectively I think at the
end the day grant Ingersoll thank you
very much for speaking to software
engineering radio thank you thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise su
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slash buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]